Oh, hello friends!
Are you wondering what this is?
Well, it's the molten lava that comes out from a volcano
Come, let me tell you what a volcano is.
Zoooom in!
I am sure you've seen mountains that open up
and blurt out thick molten semi-solid like substance?
Well, that's called a volcano!
Let’s learn more about it.
A volcano is a vent or 'chimney'
that connects Magma from within the Earth’s crust
to the Earth's surface.
The liquid rock is called Magma
when it is under the earth's surface
and Lava after it comes out.
So how does a volcano erupt?
The molten rock stored in the magma chamber
rises through the crater pipe pockets.
As it travels up the main vent,
gases expand and water becomes steam, creating pressure.
When the pressure can no longer be contained
the volcano erupts through the crater
and secondary side vents.
Common volcanic gases include
water vapour, carbon dioxide, sulfur dioxide,
hydrogen chloride, hydrogen fluoride
and hydrogen sulfide.
Popular belief is that
Volcanoes are large cone-shaped mountains but that's not true.
There are many more types of volcanoes, such as -
wide plateaus,
fissure vents
and bulging dome shapes.
There are also volcanoes found on the ocean floor
and even under icecaps
such as those found in Iceland.
The word volcano
originally comes from the name of the Roman god of fire
Vulcan
The tallest volcano in the Solar System isn’t on Earth at all
but on Mars.
So tune in next time
for some more fun filled facts.
This is me Zooomin’ out